A Guide to the Research Files of James Cox on Slavery Reparations, 1776-2002 (bulk 1997-2002)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Research Files of James Cox on Slavery Reparations 1776-2002 (bulk 1997-2002)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14178
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by James Cox, Vienna, Virginia, on March 7, 2008.
Scope and Content
The papers of James Cox consist of research files on slavery reparations for articles published in USA Today published in 2002, ca. 1,200 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet), 1835-2002.
The collection contains research files of photocopies and notes, chiefly from the 19th century railroads and financial institutions which became the 21st century defendants in a 2002 slavery reparations suit: Deadria Farmer-Paellman vs Fleetboston Financial Corporation, Aetna Inc, CSX and their predecessors, successors and/or assigns. Material copied includes slave manifests, inventories, census records, court judgments insurance policies, runaway ads, etc.
Cox's notes and photocopies of primary materials from the following institutions are present: the National Archives, U.S. Census Bureau, Montgomery Historical Society, American Textile History Museum, Museum of Jewish Heritage, Richmond Public Library, Louisiana Supreme Court, Library of Virginia, New York Historical Society, Tulane University, Virginia Historical Society, University of Virginia, University of Texas, and Harvard University.
These papers also include notes and interviews with historians and other scholars, including Richard America, Charles Ogletree, Ted Kornweibel, Richard Kilbourne, R.L. Wilson, James McPherson, Charles Dew, Walter Johnson, Philip Curtin, David Eltis, Ron Walters, Charles Blockson, and Manning Marable.
There are also notes and interviews with activists, including Deadria Farmer-Paellman, Roger Wareham and Jesse Jackson; plaintiff's lawyers, Ed Fagan, Dianne Sammons, Willie Gary, Alexander Pires, Richard Scruggs; attorneys Stuart Eizenstat of Covington and Burling, and Owen Pell of White & Case; California assemblyman Tom Hayden; Sonia Metzger, staffer for New York assemblyman Roger Green; Kriston Alford, staffer for U.S. Representative John Conyers; officials in the California Department of Insurance; and the chief librarian at the Guildhall Library of London.
Interviews and research were conducted on the following companies and businesses: Aetna, CSX, Deutsche Banc Alex Brown, Rothschilds, FleetBoston, Lehman Brothers, New York Life Insurance, West Point Stevens, JP Morgan Chase, Union Pacific Railroad, Tribune Company, Gannett, Knight Ridder, Advance/Newhouse, Norfolk Southern Railroad, Hearst, A.H. Belo, Credit Suisse First Boston, ING Barings, Lloyds of London, Penn Mutual, AIG, ACE, CIGNA, Brown Brothers Harriman, Canadian National Railway, Colt, Media General, Phelps Dodge, Morton Salt, USX, Fruit of the Loom, Entergy, and Bank of Rhode Island.
Contents List
- Articles and Essays, 1909-1968 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Articles and Essays, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Articles and Essays, 1974-1993 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Articles and Essays, 1993-2002 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Article: The Holocaust Restitution Movement in Comparative Perspective by Michael J. Bazyler, 2002 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Article: King Cotton and his Retainers by Harold D. Woodman, 1968 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Bank Research and Notes, 1992-2002 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Biographical Research and Notes, 1994-2002 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Book about Brown Brothers- Partners in Banking by John A. Kouwenhoven, 1968 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Brown Brothers Papers with Commercial Bank of Rodney, 1840-1852 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Brown Brothers Research and Notes, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Brown v. Pierce and Nicou- Fifth District Court of New Orleans Dec. 3 1887, 1837 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Drafts, 2001 August-2002 January (Box-folder 2:4)
- E-mails, 2001 July-2002 February (Box-folder 2:5)
- Insurance Research and Notes, 1854-2001 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Insurance Research and Notes, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Law Articles about Slavery, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Law and Lawyers Notes and Interviews, 1995-2002 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Legal Team, 200l August (Box-folder 2:10)
- Lehman Brothers Papers, 1854-2002 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Library of Virginia's Newspapers- Alabama- Maryland, 2001 December (Box-folder 3:2)
- Library of Virginia's Newspapers- Mississippi- Tennessee, 2001 December (Box-folder 3:3)
- Library of Virginia's Newspapers- Virginia, 2001 December (Box-folder 3:4)
- Logistics, 2001 August (Box-folder 3:5)
- News Articles, 1776-2004 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Newspaper Ads, 1799-1864 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Newspaper Ads- Notes and Research, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Notes- Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:9)
- Notes- General- Academics- [Charles] Ogletree, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:10)
- Notes- General- Others- West Point, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Notes- Lawsuits and Legislation, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 4:2)
- Notes- News Articles, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Other Leads: Bank of Rhode Island, Phelps Dodge, USX, Fruit of the Loom, Retailers, 1928-2002 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Railroads- General Research and Notes, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Railroad Research- CN & UP, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 4:6)
- Railroad Research- CSX, 1835-1850 (Box-folder 4:7)
- Railroad Research- CSX, 1839-1867 (Box-folder 4:8)
- Railroad Research- North Carolina, 1838-1863 (Box-folder 4:9)
- Railroad Research and Notes- CSX- Mobile & Ohio, Petersburg, and Western & Atlantic, 1847-1861 (Box-folder 5:1)
- Railroad Research and Notes- CSX- North Carolina & South Carolina Railroad Companies, 1850-1865 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Railroad Research and Notes- CSX- Virginia Railroad Companies, 1834-1940 (Box-folder 5:3)
- Railroad Research and Notes- NS- North Carolina & South Carolina Railroad Companies, 1857-1865 (Box-folder 5:4)
- Railroad Research and Notes- NS- Virginia Railroad Companies 1848-1868 (Box-folder 5:5)
- Railroad Research and Notes- NS- Virginia & Tennessee Railroad Company, 1855-1860 (Box-folder 5:6)
- Research about Corporations, 2002 January 25 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Research and Notes about Newspapers, 2001 December (Box-folder 5:8)
- Research and Notes on Insurance, 2002 February (Box-folder 5:9)
- Research from Online Resources, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 5:10)
- Runaway Slave Ads from Baltimore Sun, 1842-1858 (Box-folder 5:11)
- Southern Railroad Annual Reports, 1838-59, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 6:1)
- Southern Railroad Research- Articles, 1928-2001 (Box-folder 6:2)
- Southern Railroad Research- Correspondence and Online Resources, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 6:3)
- UVA Database Records, 2002 January (Box-folder 6:4)
- Textiles, 1844-2001 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Web Articles, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 6:6)
- Yale: Including Report- Yale, Slavery and Abolition, 2001 (Box-folder 6:7)